Guide to the Special Collections' general artifact collection, ca. 500-1963
Department of Special Collections
Special Collections' general artifact collection,
ca. 500-1963
Special Collections M0582
Special Collections
5.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gifts from various people.
Scope and Content
Miscellaneous artifacts, mostly related to writing or printing and including such things as papyrus fragments, palm-leaf manuscripts, medals, seals, playing cards, old eye glasses and pens, Arabic scrolls, print blocks, including six by Theo Jung, and two marble (alabaster?) busts, one of Charles Dickens and one of Dante, nd.
Access Terms
Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321.; Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.; Jung, Theo.; Busts.; Manuscripts (papyri); Medals.; Palm-leaf manuscripts.; Playing cards.; Scrolls.
Container List
- Miscellaneous artifacts
  - 1. Ivory watch-charm, oval, London & Birmingham railway; obverse: Free ticket. Reverse: James Pearson, Esq. Director, 1837.In round wooden box ca 3" dia. M474 in SUL Misc. Accessions book. Source Timothy Hopkins. (Box 1)
  - 2. Papyri in black leather case. (Box 1)
  - 3. Twenty-two 3" × 5" cards with pictures of animals and birds and accompanying poems. Pub. by Hodgson & Co. 10 Newgate St. 1824. (Box 1)
  - 4. Deck of playing cards in plastic case tied with ribbon. Case reads Essays in Science and Art. (Box 1)
  - 5. Daguerreotype of young man in 18th cent. costume. In 3½" × 4" stamped brown leather folding case. (Box 1)
  - 6. Similar to #5. (Box 1)
  - 7. Ambrotype in gold colored frame, 1½" × 2", of man in 1840s costume. Back reads Stephen Labor 1793-1823Marion's Great-Grandfather. (note: photography invented 1839.) (Box 1)
  - 8. Old fashioned octagonal wire-rimmed glasses in red case, 1" × 4". (Box 1)
  - 9. Glasses in black case. 1" × 6". (Box 1)
  - 10. Oval wire-rimmed glasses (broken earpiece), optical notations on lenses. (Box 1)
  - 11. Oval wire-rimmed glasses. (Box 1)
  - 12. Wood and cloth folding fan, (ca. 12" long when closed) printed with 1776-1876and pictures of buildings (World's Fair?). (Box 1)
  - 13. Wooden Waterman fountain pen (no. 8), with stamp Arthur A. Waterman & Co. N.Y. Self-filling At. Nov. 17 '03 & Oct. 11 '04. (Box 1)
  - 14. Quill-type pen, wood. Leroy W. Fairchild New York. No. 8. (Box 1)
  - 15. Same as #14. (Box 1)
  - 16. Clay tablets (facsimilies?) (Box 1)
  - 17. Set of Chinese characters for printing in sliding top box. (Box 1)
  - 18. Charles Dickens personal seal. (Box 1)
  - 19. Miniature bookstand with 2 miniature books. (Box 1)
  - 20. Leather book cover. (Box 1)
  - 21. 2 Arabic ? scrolls in leather-covered cube-shaped containers., He [UNK] religious [UNK] (Box 1)
  - 22. Arabic ? scroll in fret-work holder. (Box 1)
  - 23. 2 wood boards with unknown script. (Box 1)
- Wood blocks, printing devices, etc.
  - 1. SUL stamp with SU seal 4"× 2½" with rectangular hole. (Box 2)
  - 2. Letter S with floral embellishments: 2" × 1½". (Box 2)
  - 3. Leland Stanford University Libraries with landscape background. 2¼"× 1½". (Box 2)
  - 4. Peace of Mind/Good Health/Long Life. 4"× 2½". On reverse Th. Jung in pencil. (Box 2)
  - 5. God bless copper printing and every other means of duplicating, so that the good that was present can not be destroyed again. -Johann Wolfgang Goethe. Printed on the handpress in the Bender Room by the History of the Book class of Dr. Susan V. Lenkey. Stanford, Spring 1973.7½"× 4". (Box 2)
  - 6. Herzlichen Dank für die schöne Gastfreundschaft. 7½"× 6" Same in smaller size on reverse. (Box 2)
  - 7. Abstract foliage design. 1½" × 3½". On reverse Th. Jung. (Box 2)
  - 8. Ex Libris Kate Felton Elkins, on background of road with trees. 2½" × 3". (Box 2)
  - 9. Monk dreaming[?]. 2½" × 3". (Box 2)
  - 10. Abstract symbol. 1½" × 2½". Written on reverse: This block for Henry in appreciation for his support and faith. -K.J. Carpenter 4[?]/17/61. (Box 2)
  - 11. Cartoon stick figure (workman). 3/4" × 3/4". (Box 2)
  - 12. Two Chinese[?] ideograms. 1" × 2". (Box 2)
  - 13. Three Chinese[?] characters on handheld stamp. ½" × 1" × 2". (Box 2)
  - 14. Sketch of nude woman's torso (front). 6" × 3". Reverse: Th. Jung. (Box 2)
  - 15. Sketch of nude woman's torso (front). Different from 14. 6" × 4". Reverse: Th. Jung. (Box 2)
  - 16. Sketch of woman's torso (rear). 5½" × 3½". Reverse: Th. Jung. (Box 2)
  - 17. Sketch of woman's rear end and legs. 6½" × 2½". Reverse: Th. Jung. (Box 2)
  - 18. Photo print block of man (resembling Mark Twain). 5" × 3". (Box 2)
  - 19. Nineteenth-century men and woman in a drawing-room[?]. For Trollope work. 5" × 3". (Box 2)
- Medals
  - 1. M503 in SUL Misc. Accessions BK. (Dec. 13, 1935)Round bronze medal ca. 3" dia. Obverse: Portrait of man, Archibald Ashley Welch 1859-1938Reverse: Forty-five years an official of the Phoenix Mutual Life Insurance Company. President 1924-1935.In box. Source: President's Office. (Box 3)
  - 2. Misc. 3261. (May 4, 1944)Bronze medallion ca. 3" dia. Obverse: Republique Française, MDCCCLXX [1850]with goddess bearing constitution. Reverse: Les Musées Nationaux de France a Mr. Albert Bender S. Francisco 1936.Olive and oak wreath. In case. (Box 3)
  - 3. Misc. 3262. (May 4, 1944)Ribbon medal. Chevalier of the Legion of Honor, Republic of France. In case. (Box 3)
  - 4. M406. (Mar. 12, 1934)Bronze medal ca. 3" dia. Obverse: Université Libre de Bruxelles 1834-1934.Scientia vincere tenbras. and relief of cathedral. Reverse: Profile with Pierre Theodore Verhaegen 1796-1862.In round box. (Box 3)
  - 5. M373. (Sept 25, 1934)Bronze medal ca. 2½" dia. commemorating 100th anniversary of the death of Lafayette. Obverse: Profile of L., Lafayette 1757-1834.Reverse: America et Gallia Memores MCMXXXIV [1934]. (Box 3)
  - 6. M508. (Jan 24, 1935)Bronze medal ca. 3" dia. Obverse: Woman's head and Republique Français; reverse: Offert par le ministere des affaires estrangeres. In case. (Box 3)
  - 7. Silver-colored medal, 3" dia. Obverse: William Shakespeare 1564-1616,The 20th anniversary Meisei University with bust in relief. Reverse: What a piece of work is man... --Hamlet. In wooden box with Japanese[?] characters in gold. (Box 3)
  - 8. Five oval plaster cameos, ca. 1" × 2". In grey cardboard box. (Box 3)
  - 9. Round bronze medal, 3" dia. Obverse: First American Statue of Gutenberg. Erected in New York by Robert Hoe 1899,relief of G. statue. Reverse: Iohann Gaensefleisch vulgo Gutenberg - born in Mainz Germany betw. 1393-1400,bust of Gutenberg. (Box 3)
  - 10. Rectangular bronze medal, 2" × 4". Obverse: Statue of Athena. Reverse: (in Greek) Ekatontaetris Panepistmiou Athnon [100th anniversary Athens University] 1837-1937with university building, torch, and owl (symbol of Athena) with olive wreath. In case. Enclosed slip of paper reads: Gift of Dr. Hazel Hansen 6/2/39.Brought in to E.V.H. by J.M.H. (Box 3)
  - 11. Round bronze medal 3" dia. Obverse: Printing press, La Lumiere Fut. Reverse: Jean Gutenberg Inventuer de L'imprimerie Ne En 1400. Bust of G. (Box 3)
  - 12. Bronze medal 2" dia. Obverse: Armanus Ioan. Card. de Richelieu. Bust of R. Reverse: Mens sidera volvit 1631.Relief of planet and stars. (Box 3)
  - 13. Silver medal 3" dia. Obverse: Special Medal of Award, American Institute of Graphic Arts with tree: Beauty/Utility. On reverse: Man with press. Around edge: To Taylor & Taylor Silver Medal 1920. (Box 3)
  - 14. Same as 13. (Box 3)
  - 15. Bronze medallion 2½" dia. Obverse: Henri Estienne with bust of same. Reverse: Seated goddess with wreath and children. (Box 3)
  - 16. Rectangular bronze medal, 2" × 3". Obverse: Elegie with depressed woman. Reverse: Tree with broken columns. (Box 3)
  - 17. Bronze medal, 4" dia. Obverse: Robert Lee Frost 1874-1963.Relief of F. Reverse: California Friends of Robert Frost. Born San Francisco March 26, 1874.Newspaper boy/Bobbin boy/Teacher/Jounalist/Farmer/Poet. Died Boston, Mass. Jan. 29, 1963.Note: Gift of G. William Gahagan November 1973. (Box 3)
  - 18. Broken bronze medallion, 2" dia. (1 piece missing) Obverse: A. Jean Gutenberg. La Ville du Strasbourg. Portrait of G. Reverse: Inventeur de L' imprimerie. (Box 3)
  - 19. Book with enclosed medal (bronze, 3" dia.) Circle of Friends of the Medal. June 1913.Medal by Sigurd Neandross, Nymphs and sea-god. (Box 3)
  - 20. Frank G. Logan medal awarded to Miss Gertrude C. Crestwell for bookbinding (Box 3)
- Palm-leaf manuscripts
  - 1. Palm leaf pages between two elongated rectangular wooden cover-boards. Cover has painted floral decoration in light blue, painted title. Paper label Pali Gatha, No. 11. Various cataloging numbers pasted/painted on. 15" × 2½" × 1" thick. (Box 4)
  - 2. Boards have floral decoration in light blue, painted title. Paper label Pali Gatha No. 14. Assorted catalog numbers pasted/painted on. 14" × 2½" × 1". (Box 4)
  - 3. Plain natural brown wood cover boards. 16" × 2" × 2". (Box 4)
  - 4. Cover boards have gold and red incised floral designs, gilt edging on pages. Paper label inside cover reads M469. This palm leaf manuscript is the Kammavaca of the Vinaya Pitika transcribed by a Bhikchu, a Buudhist priest of laos, Farther India, and dedicated by him to the temple service. Accessioned May 9, 1935 -Bender Collection. (SUL Misc. Accessions book). 24 × 2½ × 1½". (Box 4)
  - 5. Cover boards have black and gold floral design, gilded page edges. With pointer, red and gold, on cord (cord broken). Identified as M470 in SUL Misc. Accessions book. 58 × 8½ × 5 cm. (Box 4)
  - 6. Mss. with plain brown wood boards, 20" × 2½" × 2". (Box 4)
  - 7. Boards two of black and gold floral design on orange-red, stylized birds with intertwined necks. Inside covers are buddhas[?] in white on deep blue background. 21" × 2" × 2½". (Box 4)
- Busts
  - 1. 1 Marble bust of Charles Dickens (Box 5)
  - 2. 1 marble bust of Dante Alighieri (Box 5)